Guide to the United Steelworkers of America Local 1397 (Homestead, Pa.) Records, 1937-1972 AIS.1993.17
ULS Archives & Special Collections
United Steelworkers of America Local 1397 (Homestead, Pa.) Records
1937-1972
ULS Archives & Special Collections
United Steelworkers of America. Local 1397 (Homestead, Pa.)
AIS.1993.17
6.5 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
This collection contains documents once in the possession of John McManigal, president of United Steelworkers of America Local 1397, 1964-1970. Included are minute books, union contracts and pension agreements, the Local 1397 newspaper The Sentinel, union election materials, and other documents.
History
United Steelworkers of America Local 1397 was chartered in 1937 as a local of the Steelworkers Organizing Committee. The history of unionism at the Homestead works prior to this had been a storied one. The Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel and Tin Workers of America first unionized skilled workers there in the 1880s, but the Amalgamated lodge suffered a monumental defeat at the hands of Andrew Carnegie, Henry Clay Frick and the Pennsylvania National Guard in the months following the famous Battle of Homestead in 1892. Thereafter, notwithstanding a dramatic attempt at organization in 1918, unionism at the Homestead works was moribund or underground, until the 1930s, when a new wave of industrial unionism carried the day in the steel, automotive, electrical, and other industries. John McManigal was president of Local 1397 from 1964 to 1970. His contributions to the union also included editorship of the local's award winning newspaper, The Sentinel.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection is made up of records generated by the officers and members of Local 1397. Materials include: minute books kept by the executive committee and shop stewards; local union publications and print plates used in these publications; election materials; papers collected by John McManigal during his presidency of the union and as editor of The Sentinel; and union agreements, including: contracts, pension agreements, etc.
Arrangement
Missing Title
Series I. Minute Books, 1937-1944
Series II. The Sentinel
Series III. Election Materials, 1956-1970
Series IV. Publications, 1950-1969
Series V. Contracts, Benefit Booklets, and Related Union Materials, 1949-1970
Series VI. John McManigal, 1958-1972
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John McManigal, son of the collector of the records, 1933.
Existence and Location of Copies
The Sentinel, located in Series II, is available on microfilm. (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7)
Previous Citation
United Steelworkers of America Local 1397 (Homestead, Pa.) Records, 1937-1972, AIS.1993.17, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
United Steelworkers of America Local 1397 (Homestead, PA) Records, 1937-1972, UE/Lab 199317, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Pittsburgh and Western Pennsylvania Labor Legacy Website: http://www.library.pitt.edu/labor_legacy/
Separated Material
The microfilm of The Sentinel is stored separately.
Oversize materials are located in Range 1/14/3.
Labor union meetings -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Labor unions -- Elections; Labor unions -- Elections -- Law and legislation -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Collective labor agreements -- Steel industry and trade -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Labor unions -- Officials and employees; The Sentinel; Minute books; Appointment books; Labor; Newsletters; Photographs; Contracts; Testimonies; Pittsburgh (Pa.); McManigal, John; United Steelworkers of America. Local 1397 (Homestead, Pa.)
- Minute Books, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains one original and two copied minute books of each the executive committee and the shop steward. The meetings of the executive committee were generally closed to union members and the main purpose of the meetings was to set local union policy. The executive committee minutes were recorded by the following Recording Secretaries: James Marsh (April 1937-June 1938), Lee Thomas (July 1938-May 1939) J.D. Molteram (June 1939- June 1941), and Joseph Carter (July 1942-March 1944). The shop steward's function was to organize and represent the men in the grievance process, and the stewards' minute book (February - October 1940) provides among other details, the percentages of men in each steward's jurisdiction enrolled as union members during those months. The minutes of the stewards meetings were kept by the secretary, Joseph Carter.
  - Original Shop Stewards Minute Book and Use Copies, February 1940-October 1940 (Box 1)
  - Original Executive Committee Minute Book and Use Copies, April 1937-March 1944 (Box 2)
- The Sentinel, II.
  Included with this series is a run of the local publication, The Sentinel. Also included in this series is a set of print plates and print plate copies used in the production of The Sentinel.
  - Unfoldered Issues of The Sentinel (Box 3)
  - Original Print Plates
  - Copy Print Plates, Cartoons (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Copy Print Plates, Photos (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
- Election Materials, III.
  Included with this series is all correspondence, manuals, trial transcriptions, and other information relating to union elections during the 1960s.
  - Campaign memorabilia (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Election dispute: Lawrence McDonald v. Andrew Toth, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Election dispute: Lawrence McDonald v. Andrew Toth, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - International Officers Convention Atlantic City, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - International election, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Local officers, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Local Union Elections Manual, 1956, 1967, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper clippings of 1969 dispute (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Publications of the "Party with a Purpose", 1964 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Publications, IV.
  This series is made up of publications collected by John McManigal during his presidency of Local 1397.
  - The 1959 Steel Strike (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - AFL-CIO: Booklets, 1959, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Hoffman, Paul G.: Booklets, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Highlights of Crucial 1952 Strike (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - International Labor Press Association (ILPA): News Releases, 1957-1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago Industrial Relations Center: Leadership in a Local Union, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Man's Magazine: "The Strike That Turned to War", March 1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - National Safety Council: Labor Safety Newsletter, May- June 1959 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Pennsylvania Department of Labor: Safe Practices Recommendations, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Special...Steel Labor, June 1956; July, Sept.-Dec. 1959; Feb. 1960; June-July 1961 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - United Rubber Workers: Labor Scrapbook, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - U.S. Department of Labor: Booklets, 1967, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The U.S. Steel Quarterly: "Aftermath of the Labor Settlement", Feb. 1960 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Steelabor inscribed "Richard Miller" (Oversize 1)
- Contracts, Benefit Booklets, and Related Union Materials, V.
  This series is made up of copies of by-laws, contracts, pension agreements, and other agreements between the union and employers. It also contains president's appointment books and records of other union business. The portion containing union contracts and benefit booklets is organized chronologically so many types of agreements may be housed in one folder.
  - USWA Agreement with U.S. Steel, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - USWA Agreement with U.S. Steel, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - USWA Agreement with U.S. Steel, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - USWA Agreement with U.S. Steel, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Medical Benefits for Pernsioners, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Program of Employee Insurance Benefits, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Pension Agreement, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Pension Agreement, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Supplemental Unemployment Benefit Plan, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Supplemental Unemployment Benefit Plan, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Savings and Vacation Plan, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Savings and Vacation Plan, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - USWA By-Laws for Local Unions, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - USWA Local 1397 Munhall, PA. By-Laws (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - "These Are Our People", 1956 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Proceedings of the 12th Constitutional Convention of the USWA, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Proceedings of the 13th Constitutional Convention of the USWA, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Proceedings of the 14th Constitutional Convention of the USWA, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Proceedings of the Special International Convention of the USWA, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Proceedings of the 15th Constitutional Convention of the USWA, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Annual Reports, 1949-1953 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Articles of Local 1397 (articles of a proposed constitution) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Presidential desk calendars, 1968-1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - General correspondence, 1952-1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Report on hazardous conditions in open Hearth No. 5 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Lost time by union financial officers (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous memos and notes (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1959, 1962, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Supplemental Seniority Agreement, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Testimony before Select Committee on Labor (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Union contracts and benefit booklets
    - 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - 1950 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - 1952, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - 1956, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - 1960 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - No Date (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - News releases (Box 7, Folder 20)
- John McManigal, VI.
  The series consists of journalistic awards received by John McManigal during the time he served as editor of The Sentinel. It also includes photos and newspaper clippings.
  - Certificates of award, 1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence with John McManigal, 1958-1961 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Journalistic awards, 1959, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Photographs and newspaper clippings, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Public Interest Award, 1959-1962 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - University Labor Press contests, 1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 26)